當我剛才一路參與崇拜的時候
都是非常之感動
因為太老大兄姊妹
他們用心的採排
他們的練習
亦都是一齊好像見證著神
在我們教會的恩典
I am really thankful when I hear
and when I see
what the brother and sister prepared for us
in this celebration
I am really touched
They put their heart into it
and also we can witness
God is among us
and the grace of God is amongst us
當我剛才參加我們的
集體崇拜的時候
我感到非常的感動
因為弟兄姊妹為這次的崇拜
也準備了很多
我們看到神在我們當中的工作
So today I am preparing
when I prepare the message that
sometimes you know as a pastor
year after year
every year in the anniversary
that I need to prepare something
sometimes it seems like
what do I want to preach today
今天我在準備我的講道的時候
我感到就是有一點
因為我經常一次又一次的
要準備這個講道
So get back to the topic then
the title is
The Feeling of Repetitive Age
我今天準備的講道的題目是
活在不斷輪迴的世代
So I'm guarantee that my message
is not the repetition
我可以保證我的信息
並不是重複以前
Yeah, every time is new
每一次都是新的
So one day while I was working
in my womb that
I heard my daughter listening her music
有一次我在我房間工作的時候
我聽到我的女兒在聽她的音樂
The song she was playing surprised me
當中的這個歌曲讓我感到很吃驚
I didn't recognize this young singer
However, the style
that really surprised me
我並不認識這個年輕的歌手
驚訝的也不單單是當中的歌詞
It's not the lyrics
but the beat and the singing style
and the arrangement of the music
that clearly is remnants
of the style of 50s and 60s
我驚訝的是她的這些節拍
唱法或者是編排
明明就是五六十年代的風格
I wonder why a young singer
would create and sing such kind of songs
我很奇怪一個年輕的歌手
為什麼會唱這樣的歌呢
Later I asked Caitlin
why you are listening to these songs
with 50s and 65s
後來我問凱琳
為什麼她會聽這些
六十年代的這些舊歌
So she said
This singer is one of the most popular artists today
and many of her castmates also listen to her
但是她說這個歌手
是最近很流行的一個歌手
而且她的同學都在聽
Have you noticed that
despite the rapid advancement of the technology
people always seem to yearn for the past
大家有沒有留意到
雖然現在的科技
在不斷的日新月異
但是人們總是在緬懷過去
We like to present the old memories in the new ways
我們只是用新的方法
來緬懷以前的回憶
It's like a teenager
watching an old episode of Friends
on the streaming platform
就好像一個十多歲的孩子
在這個平台上
還繼續的收看
Friends 老友記這樣的舊節目
As if in the movie
Guardian of the Galaxy
the protagonist remnants
the songs of 80s and 90s
就是在好像在銀河保衛隊中的
電影主角緬懷的
卻都是八九十年代的舊歌
Hollywood earned a big money
by remaking all those classics
這個好萊塢也要花很大的價錢
卻是不斷的翻拍以往的經典的電影
You can think about
I can name a few
You know Top Gun
Doom live action
Disney movie
and Mad Max
and even the reason is inside out
就好像Top Gun
還有這個沙丘
這個計劃
或者是真版的沙丘
這個真人版的
這個Disney的電影
Mad Max
或者最近大家可能知道
Inside Out 2
You know what
Even NASA
Today's business project
is getting back to the moon
你們知道嗎
甚至美國太空總署
最忙碌的計劃
卻是重返地球
It's as if we are living in a society
that suffer from Alzheimer's disease
我們好像生活在一個老年痴呆症的社會
We feel lost when we're looking ahead
That's why we cannot create new memory
for the future
因為對前面的感覺很迷茫
所以對將來的事情
我們沒有辦法產生新的記憶
So we can only keep reminiscing
about the so-called Golden Age of the past
我們只能對著以往的所謂的黃金歲月
不斷地去緬懷
New idea actually get us nowhere
But the new technology application
continuously repeat the glorious day of the past
新的思想並沒有突破
新科技的應用
卻是在不斷地重複
以往的光輝歲月
It's like a popular thesis
being repeated over and over
But just with new fonts and new formatting
But the content remain the same
就好像一篇很受歡迎的論文
雖然配上了新的字體和編排的格式
卻不斷地印刷
但是內容都是一樣的
The preacher described this deeply
in the Achaiasis
傳道者在傳道書中有深切的描繪
我讀完這一段
OK
The sun's wise and the sun's sad
And hurry back to where it rises
The wind blows to the south
And turn to the north
One and one it goes
Ever returning on its course
All streams fall into the sea
Yet the sea is never full
To the place of the streams come from
There they return again
All things are wearisome
More than one can say
The eyes never has enough of seeing
Long the year is filled of hearing
What has been will be again
What has been done will be done again
There is nothing new under the sun
哇 這個很長
日頭出來 日頭又落下
即歸所出之處
風往南瓜 又往北轉
不住地旋轉
而且返回原來的道路
江河都往海裡面流
但是海卻不滿
江河從何處流出來
又歸回何處
萬事都令人厭煩
人卻不能說盡
眼看看不飽
耳聽聽不足
已有的事 事後必再有
已行的事 事後必再行
日光之下無心事
How can we convey the gospel
that brings hope in this era?
在這樣的一個時代
我們如何能夠傳遞
使人有盼望的福音呢
保羅稱我們的神是有盼望的神
Jeremiah 29 11說
For I know the pants I have for you
Declare the Lord pants to prosper you
and not to harm you
pants to give you hope and future
在耶利米說
二十九章十一節耶和華說
我知道我向你們所懷的意念
是指平安的意念
不是講災禍的意念
是要叫你們末後有指望
Hope and meaning are inseparable
這個盼望和意義是分不開的
When we don't have hope
When we don't have meaning
Everything just repeat again
現在的人的困境就好像
一切都沒有意義
一切都沒有方向
看到的事情是不斷的在重複的
The current predicament of people
is that everything seems meaningless
and directionless
and with events constantly repeating themselves
As Achaeus says
Meaningless, meaningless
Everything is meaningless
What has happened
It will happen again
現在的困境
人的困境就好像
一切都沒有意義
沒有方向
也看不到事情的
不斷的重複
就好像傳道書中所說
沒有意義
虛空的虛空
以前發生的事情
就必然會重新再來
But those of us who trust in the law
do not see the world this way
但是我們相信神的人
不是這樣看世界的
We firmly believe that the law
still have his plan to this world
我們相信我們的主
還是這個世界的主
Although the world is chaotic
but God is still in control
雖然這個世界很混亂
但是神仍然掌權
God still have his plan for this created world
and especially for those who believe in him
神對信他的人
和他所創造的世界
是有他的計劃的
所以事情是可以有意義的
Therefore things can still be meaningful
Because of this belief
we see that the events happen
not just its meaningless repetition
正因為這樣的堅信
我們看到了
這個發生的事情
不是沒有意義的重複
We seek to live out the meaning
and purpose in every day
我們尋求活出的意義和目的
在每天的日常生活當中
In the seemingly repetitive daily routine
we contemplate
how can we fulfill God's will in it
我們的思想
怎樣可以在每天的生活當中
完成神的旨意
神的旨意總是好的
and His will ultimately
will lead to perfect conclusion
神的旨意總是好的
祂的旨意最終能夠
成就美好的結局
When we live with a reference heart
we participate in God's plan
through our mundane routine
我們用敬畏的心
在每天的生活當中
以行動來參與神的計劃
We therefore do not remain stuck
in the women's scene
我們不會停留在
只是在緬懷過去
We seize the present
我們要掌握現在
Take advantage of today's opportunities
我們要把握今天的機會
and hope to advance the purpose
and the kingdom of God
這樣就可以配合神的旨意
推進天國的目的
Then you may ask
How can someone as insignificant as I
推進 the kingdom of God?
接著你可能會問
哎呀 我這個人這麼樣的渺小
我怎麼能推進天國的事業呢?
這真的是一個很合理的問題
Indeed, if we look at ourselves alone
we feel that we are incapable of influence
in this godless world
的確 如果我們只是看重自己
就真的不會對這個
沒有上帝的世界
有什麼樣的影響
But brother and sister
We are not fighting this battle alone
但是弟兄姊妹們
我們並不是在孤身奮戰
When we understand that
the vision of God's kingdom
We realize that
kingdom itself is a collective concept
當我們明白天國的意向
我們就明白天國呢
他是一個群體的概念
Kingdom's vision
is also the vision of the church
天國的意向也是教會的意向
Instead of asking how I
as an insignificant individual
can influence the world
以及問我 人這樣的渺小
怎麼能夠影響這個世界
We should ask how we
can become a community
that bear witnesses to Christ
我們不如去問
我們怎樣才能成為一個
見證基督的群體
To influence the world
We will ask what kind of community we are
要影響世界
我要問我們是一個怎樣的群體呢
Do we love each other
我們當中有愛嗎
我們彼此相愛嗎
Do we accept those
who are different from us
我們有寬恕和接納
和我們不同的人嗎
Do we care for
to reach out for those in need
我們有關心這些需要我們幫助的人嗎
Do we forgive those who offense us
我們有寬恕原諒那些
得罪我們的人嗎
Do we constantly reminding
how to lead others to Christ
我們有常常的想到
怎樣讓人認識耶穌基督嗎
Do we put aside our interest
and work together for the kingdom
that the church want to advance
我們有沒有謙卑自己
懷著同樣的這個心思
一同為教會
所推進的天國的施工努力呢
By focusing on this question
and act upon them
We become a strong and united body
capable of making a significant impact
通過關注這些問題
如果付諸行動的話
我們就可以成為一個
強大而團結的身體
能夠產生重大的影響
Our collective effort
driven by love, forgiveness, care
and shared vision
can truly advance the cause of the kingdom
我們如果集體的努力
由愛、寬恕和共同的願景所驅動
我們就能夠推進神國的事業
Just recently
we complete the 40-day campaign of SHAPE
剛剛我們完成了
40天的生命特製的運動
If you look at the campaign
with the self-centered perspective
it will always be somewhat lacking
那如果我們只是專注於看自己
我們總會感到這是美中不足的
No matter how much self-awareness
we gain in the campaign
if we focus mainly solely on ourselves
we risk becoming a self-centered individual
in this consumeristic culture
因為我們無論對自己
有多少的認識
如果你只是專注在自己身上的話
在這個消費主義的現代社會當中
我們還是會成為一個以自我為中心的人
The main focus of the 40-day campaign
is Christ, not ourselves
在這個40天的學習運動當中的主角
不是我們而是基督
The emphasis should be on the kingdom
not about self-fulfillment
這個重點應該是天國
而不是我們自我的實現
We must understand that
finding our own shape
is about discover our place in that kingdom
我們要明白自己是獨特的形狀的
是為了這個目的是為了找到
自己在天國當中的位置
What role will you play in that kingdom?
你在天國當中要有什麼樣的位置呢
How can you proactively take responsibility
and express your own shape?
你是不是可以主動的承擔責任
發揮獨特的你呢
No one can replace you
if you do not participate in church
沒有人可以取代你
如果你不參加在這個教會當中
The church is the body of Christ
這個教會就是基督的身體
I once used an analogy in the Cantonese congregation
A person with two eyes
我曾經講過一個比喻
就是一個人有兩隻眼睛
If one eye chooses not to see
Don't you say that
the other eye can replace the non-seeing eye?
如果你的一隻眼睛選擇不看見
你就不能只說
他還有另外一隻眼睛
A person with one non-functioning eye
can only see with other eyes
另外一隻眼睛就是
可以取代不看的眼睛嗎
一個人他有一隻用的眼睛
他就只能用一隻眼來看
Even though the seeing eyes can still see
but the person only have a monocular vision
雖然有一隻眼睛看
但是這個人呢
他只是有一個眼睛的視野
The seeing eyes cannot replace the non-seeing eyes
這個有點繞口啊
這個看的眼睛啊
他是不能夠取代那一隻不看的眼睛的
Do you understand brother and sister?
你們明白嗎?弟兄姊妹
You are you
你就是你
You are unique
Your gifts and talents
If you don't engage in the word of Christ
Nobody can replace you
你的獨特 你的恩賜 你的才能
你若不參加天國的施工
天國就是少了你
沒有人可以取代你的
And the kingdom is missing something
that only you can provide
這個天國呢就失去你了
沒有人可以取代
As mentioned earlier
we live in a consumeristic society
where people lost their sense of purpose and meaning
就像我們剛才講的我們是生活在一個消費主義的社會當中
人失去了目的和意義
Lacking direction and get caught in the endless cycles of consumption and memories
他們沒有向錢的方向就只能不停的在回憶當中打圈圈
But we can offer people's hope
我們一同參加成為天國的群體的話
我們就能夠讓人看見盼望
When we participate together to become a community
to bear witness to God's kingdom
then we can offer people's hope
我們一同參加的話
我們就能讓人看見盼望
在沒有認識的人當中看到我們生命的話
就看到我們是有這個
So those of us who don't know God
They can see our lives
and realize that we live with purpose and meaning
如果他們在我們身上看見的話
他們就看到我們是有意義來活著的
When they can see us our life change and can move forward
They can see meaning
當他們在我們身上看見的時候
他們就認識到我們是有意義的
When they see that our mindset is not waiting to die
but hoping for resurrection
They can see meaning
是的 他們如果在我們身上看見可以改變向錢的話
就知道這個意義了
活出這樣的意義
And that is the testimony we can give to this world
這就是我們可以給這個世界的見證
When we live out this life
we can harness the gospel influence
so that become the most powerful testimony for God in this age
當我們活出這樣的生命
我們就發揮了福音的影響力
就能夠在這個不幸的時代
活出最有力的見證
I'm not saying that it will be easy and smooth
我並不是說這個過程是很容易的是很順利的
But we can overcome with joys
because we live in God's grace
但是我們能夠得勝靠著神的恩典
We can celebrate and shout together with the psalmist
The Lord has done great thing for us
and we are filled with joy
我們可以和這個詩人一起慶祝和歡呼
耶和華果然為我們行了大事
我們就歡喜
So brother and sister
How we live for the God's kingdom
is the most powerful witnesses to the gospel
所以弟兄姊妹們
我們如何為天國而活
就是在這個不幸的時代中
Some say that evangelism is very difficult today
我們如何活呢
就是為這個世代的福音做最好的見證
有人說這個時代傳福音不容易
I agree
要 我同意的
It's like a shoe salesman arriving in a village
that nobody wears shoes
就好像一個賣鞋的商人
他到了一個村莊沒有人穿鞋
You can say that selling shoes in this village
is very difficult
你可以說他要在這個村莊賣鞋
太不容易了
But if he can successfully demonstrate
how wearing shoes can make walking easier
allow you to walk further and prevent injuries
His demonstration actually can make his business success
但是他如果能夠示範給別人
他怎麼樣穿著鞋走路
怎麼樣能夠走得更遠
走得更容易
而且還不用擔心腳被刺傷
那他就可以成功的賣掉這個鞋
The success of his business
is about his demonstration
how to walk with that shoes
他成功的賣鞋是因為他示範怎麼走路
That's the most powerful testimony
in this seemingly repetition and meaningless age
這是一個非常非常有力的見證
怎樣的為天國而活
是我們最有力的見證
So let me conclude with Paul's words
in Philippians 1st chapter 27 to 28
所以我現在想用一個保羅在菲律賓書
一章的話作為總結來互相的鼓勵
Whatever happens
Conduct yourself in a manner
worthy of the gospel of Christ
Then whether I come and see you
or only hear about you in my absence
I will know that you stand firm in the one spirit
striving together as one of the faith of the gospel
without being frightened in any way by those who oppose you
This is the sign to them that they will be destroyed
but you will be saved and dead by God
經文說只要你們行事為人
以基督的福音相襯
叫我或來見你們或不在你們中間
都可以聽到你們的狀況
知道你們有同一個心智
站立的穩
為所信的福音齊心的努力
凡事不怕敵人的驚嚇
這是證明了他們沉淪
而你們得救了
May God be all the glory
這都是出於神
願榮耀歸於主